Okay. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ה. Daf
He. As I was have announced to people, but now for everybody
who's watching and listening, after today, I am no longer going to
be giving the דף יומי. Daf Yomi. Pretty much all of the
דף daf is available on YouTube and iTunes and the ישיבה's yeshiva
website, although I think some sections are missing from the ישיבה's yeshiva
website. We'll work to get that up as quickly as possible. So,
and we will hopefully be having somebody take over for me. There'll
probably be a hiatus of about a week or two. So, ask
everybody to check back in periodically. But for those people for that
hiatus and for those people who want to continue to hear my
שיעורים, shiurim, even though I won't be giving it new and live,
I've given it now for more than a full cycle and all
of that, we'll make sure is available on iTunes and YouTube and
hopefully you can get it there. So to resume, we're now picking
up on דף ה Daf He and very first line. And the
point and we're working with the teaching of רב, Rav, who said
that if that
he introduced a new idea, which seemed to go against the silence
of the משנה, Mishna, first משנה Mishna both in זבחים Zevachim and
in מנחות, Menachot, that קרבנות korbanot that are brought להכשיר l'hachshir to
change a status, if it's שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, then that means
two things. It means that it wasn't effective in changing the status.
And number two, it means the entire קרבן korban is invalid because
its whole identity and purpose is focused on that effectiveness of changing
status. So for a מנחה, mincha, that means the עומר, omer, which
is all about making the new grain permissible. So if it's not
going to have that effect because it's שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, the
whole thing is invalid. And by a קרבן, korban, it means he
specifically focused on the אשם asham of a נזיר nazir and a
מצורע, metzora, which is coming to change their status as a process
of by מצורע metzora making him טהור, tahor, by a טמא tamei
נזיר nazir who was טמא tamei making him be able to begin
his נזירות בטהרה. nezirut b'tahara. He didn't mention a חטאת, chatas, which
plays a regular role in purification because we already know that a
חטאת שלא לשמו chatas shelo lishmo is invalid. But that meant, as
the גמרא Gemara asked, that things that are coming לכפר l'chaper to
atone, which also should seem to be fundamentally about their effect, that
could be valid. That's a little ironic. An אשם asham that is
coming to atone, a חטאת chatas as we know is invalid, but
an אשם asham that's coming to atone, even if it's not going
to atone, that's still meaningful. But when it's coming להכשיר l'hachshir to
change status, if it can't do it, it's not meaningful. And the
explanation I gave is something that's coming לכפר l'chaper is fundamentally being
offered to God. It's a קרבן korban and the לכפר l'chaper is
an outgrowth of that. But therefore, even if it's not achieving לכפר,
l'chaper, it's still fundamentally a קרבן korban and that would be the
אשם. asham. Whereas something להכשיר, l'hachshir, a ritual of changing status, we
know of rituals of changing status that are not קרבנות, korbanot, right?
We know about like, you know, מקוה mikvah and פרה אדומה para
aduma and the whole thing. Well yes, but even in the טומאה
וטהרה tuma v'tahara world. So therefore you can say it's not fundamentally
about a קרבן. korban. Now עומר omer is a little strange to
include in that because עומר omer I would
say it's because you're bringing your first grain as a קרבן korban
to השם Hashem that it results in מתיר matiring the grain. It's
not just a ritual. It is fundamentally a קרבן. korban. But anyway,
that's his position, that things that are coming להכשיר l'hachshir as opposed
to things that are coming לכפר, l'chaper,
if it's שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, they're not effective and if they're
not effective they're פסול. pasul. Okay, and there are some things that
are coming להכשיר l'hachshir but they're not necessarily only identified that way,
like the multiple קרבנות korbanot of a נזיר nazir at the end
of his period, and therefore that would not apply. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues and it's going to
basically
completely show a direct contradiction to this position. Top of ה עמוד
א. He Amud Aleph.
So it says, מיתיבי, Meitivei, first end of the first line: אשם
מצורע שנשחט שלא לשמו asham metzora shenishchat shelo lishmo או שלא ניתן
מדמו אגבי בהונות. o shelo nitan midamo agabi behonot. So here is
exactly his case, רב's Rav case. An אשם מצורע asham metzora that
was שלא לשמו shelo lishmo or that it was not used, the
blood wasn't used in the ritual that it was supposed to be
used in, the blood, okay it was put on the מזבח mizbeach
as a קרבן korban but it wasn't used to put on the
thumbs and therefore did not was not able to, you know, do
what it needed to do to purify the מצורע. metzora. So in
that case, הרי זה עולה לגבי מזבח, harei zeh oleh l'gabi mizbeach,
you can still put it on the altar even if it's not
effectively being מטהר mitaher him. Here's an interesting way more than the
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo that it's not being מטהר mitaher him. You
just didn't use the blood
on the thumbs. You put the blood on the מזבח, mizbeach, you
spilled the rest of it, whatever, exactly, you spilled the rest of
it. So there's no way it's effectively, it had the potential of
being מכשיר machshir but it didn't effectively do it. Go ahead, it's
still a קרבן, korban, put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. וטעון נסכים,
v'teun nesachim, and you bring נסכים nesachim with it, which is interesting.
It still has its identity as an אשם מצורע asham metzora which
comes with נסכים, nesachim, normally an אשם asham doesn't come with נסכים.
nesachim. So even that identity still remains, but it doesn't change his
status. וצריך אשם אחר להכשירו, ve-tsarich asham acher l'hachshiro, you have to
bring another אשם asham in order to get him to change his
status. Okay, and to make him no longer a מצורע. metzora. So
anyway, it's very clear שלא לשמו shelo lishmo by an אשם מצורע
asham metzora is still effective. תיובתא דרב. Tiyuvta de-Rav. I mean not
effective, but it's still kosher. So that's a clear contradiction of Rav,
which anyway was going against the פשט pshat of all the משניות
mishnayot of the or you know of the two major opening משניות.
mishnayot. Anyway, so we now have just rejected Rav, end of story.
Now comes ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and he's going to say Rav's
idea not by אשם מצורע, asham metzora, he's going to say Rav's
idea only limited to the first case of Rav, by the עומר,
Omer, and the logic is actually a more specific logic by עומר.
Omer. So let's take a look. ריש לקיש אומר, Reish Lakish omer,
or actually no, he's not going to say it by excuse me,
he's not going to say it by עומר, Omer, but the גמרא
Gemara is going to focus on a logic that is specific by
עומר Omer that makes Rav's position more persuasive by
עומר. Omer. ריש לקיש אומר, Reish Lakish omer, מנחת עומר שקמצה שלא
לשמו כשרה. Minchat Omer she-kematzah shelo lishmah kesherah. So if it's done
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's kosher, again, against what Rav said, even
if it's not effectively coming to מתיר matir the grain. Okay, ושיריה
אינם נאכלין. u-sheyareyha einam ne'echalin. Okay, but now he points out, even
if I'm going to say it's kosher, we have to deal with
another issue, which is it's not yet, it's from the new grain,
and the עומר Omer yet hasn't been brought. The עומר Omer that's
מתיר matir the new grain hasn't been brought. You brought this עומר
Omer from the new grain. It did not have the effect of
מתיר matiring the new grain because it's שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. That
we agree with Rav, that if it's שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's
not a מתיר. matir. Okay, and therefore even if the קרבן korban
is kosher, it's made with טרף treif grain, with grain that's forbidden
to be eaten. So you can't eat the remainder. Okay, so what
do you do?
Just put it on the מזבח? mizbeach?
Yeah, or you wait for it to become פסול pasul because of
נותר notar and you burn it.
No, but which is the preferred option?
No, you have to wait for it to be נותר notar because
it's not a קרבן, korban, the שיריים, shiyaryim, so you wait for
it to be נותר notar and you burn it. עד שתביא מנחת
עומר אחרת ותתירנה. Ad she-tavi minchat omer acheret ve-tatirenah. Or what you
do is you bring another מנחת עומר Minchat Omer later that day
and you do it right this time and you do it לשמו
lishmo and then you can eat the grain. Okay, but until that
other עומר Omer is brought, the שיריים shiyaryim can't be eaten. So
now, once that's true, that then raises an argument to say what
Rav said not by an אשם נזיר מצורע, asham nazir metzora, not
by anything that's coming להכשיר, l'hachshir, but it raises the possibility of
Rav's argument by the מנחת עומר Minchat Omer because for a different
reason, not this generic "if it's not effective as a מתיר, matir,
it's פסול". pasul But if the grain itself can't be eaten, maybe
that should invalidate it. Not just say you can't eat it and
you'll have to burn it or you'll wait till the other one
is brought. Maybe the fact that you brought a קרבן korban with
grain that couldn't be eaten is itself a reason to say that
it's פסול. pasul. Okay, and that's the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara. So that at least, again, it's not what Rav said, Rav
made it broader. Okay, right. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it's
kosher. But I'm just pointing out that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish has
made us aware of a reason to say Rav's idea just by
the מנחת עומר Minchat Omer and not by the אשם נזיר. asham
nazir. Not because it's not effective, not because something that's coming להכשיר
l'hachshir that isn't effective is פסול. pasul. But if this wasn't effective,
then it was brought with טרף treif grain. Okay, so that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. מכדי היכי קרבה? Michdi heichi karvah? How could
you bring it? ממשקה ישראל? Mi-mashkeh Yisrael? It says that you have
to bring stuff from the drinks of Israel. הפסוק ביחזקאל, ha-pasuk be-Yechezkel,
you have to bring stuff from the drinks of Israel, מן המותר
לישראל, min ha-muttar l'Yisrael, and the דרשה drashah we make is that
a קרבן korban has to be made out of food that a
Jew can eat. It has to be a קרבן korban can only
be out of kosher food. If you have a reason that the
קרבן korban is not kosher, like טרפה treifah would be an obvious
example, but we have another פסוק pasuk to base that on. Let's
say you bring a מנחה minchah from I don't
know, from כלאי הכרם, kil'ei ha-kerem, you know, from grain that was
כלאיים, kil'ayim, right? So that's טרף treif קרבן korban because it's not
ממשקה ישראל. mi-mashkeh Yisrael. Something that's made out of food that's not
מותר muttar to be eaten. So therefore the קומץ kometz should be
פסול. pasul. Since the קומץ kometz wasn't מתיר חדש, matir chadash, it
was being brought from טרף treif grain and it should be פסול.
pasul. So that's an interesting reason. Not this generic idea that a
מכשיר machshir that doesn't isn't מכשיר machshir is פסול. pasul. But by
the עומר Omer if it's not מכשיר, machshir, if it's not מתיר
matir the grain, then the עומר Omer itself should be פסול. pasul.
But what's the difference between what you said, you know, כלאי הכרם
kil'ei ha-kerem you can never bring it, whereas this you're supposed to
bring it, you just did something wrong along the way.
Right, but that means that this exact, this one קרבן korban that
I am putting right now, this קומץ kometz I'm putting on the
מזבח mizbeach right now is טרף treif grain. It doesn't matter what
the reason was, right now it's טרף treif food that's being put
on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so that is a very good argument.
So, I mean not an argument, but now it's a question on
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said it's מותר.
muttar. But again, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish by making this point makes
us realize, oh, maybe that's what Rav was talking about at least
in the עומר Omer case. But anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says,
so what's the answer? Why would the קרבן korban be מותר muttar
according to ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar
Rav Adda bar Ahava, קסבר ריש לקיש, kasavar Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish is of the opinion אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום. ein
mechussar zman le-vo va-yom. If something is going to be fit later
that day... day, it's not considered that it's not yet the time.
Now, that idea can be used in a much more limited way,
right, the question like the גמרא Gemara brings this up way back
in זבחים Zvachim about why is a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach when
I sanctify, if you say for example בעלי חיים נדחין, Ba'alei Chaim
Nidchin, that even if an animal is alive if it's not fit
to be brought as a קרבן, Korban, it's, you know, it's נדחה,
Nidcheh, it's pushed away and can't be used, why when I sanctify
a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach the morning of the fourteenth, why isn't
it נדחה? Nidcheh? Because it can't be brought the morning of the
fourteenth and then it shouldn't be כשר Kosher later. And the answer
is אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום. Ein Mechusar Zman L'vo Bayom. No,
if something can be brought later today, it's not considered that it's
not its time yet and it's pushed away. But that's where the
only problem of it was, the only reason to invalidate was because
it's not yet its time, and then you're going to say the
time is coming later today, it is its time. Here we're saying
a different point. Here what we're saying is that the food itself
is not כשר. Kosher. It's literally not כשר. Kosher. If you ate
it, you would transgress the negative prohibition, but because later today it
will be כשר, Kosher, when we are not asking the question if
Michael ate from this he would transgress and we'd give him lashes,
okay, we wouldn't say Michael ate but it's going to be מותר
Muttar later today, it's like who the heck cares, right now you
ate טריף Treif food. Okay, but if the question is is it
כשר Kosher as a קרבן Korban and where the הלכה Halacha of
if something is כשר Kosher of a קרבן Korban is is it
made out of food that is כשר Kosher for a יהודי Yehudi
to eat, the answer is since this will be כשר Kosher for
a יהודי Yehudi to eat later today, because later today you're going
to bring another מנחת העומר, Minchat HaOmer, it's supposed to be brought
on the sixteenth of פסח Pesach of ניסן, Nisan, so since it
will be כשר Kosher to be eaten later today, it's considered already
כשר Kosher as a קרבן. Korban. Okay, so again, it's not the
normal אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום Ein Mechusar Zman L'vo Bayom because
here there already is a very present problem, it's not כשר. Kosher.
But we say but in terms of determining its status as a
fit קרבן, Korban, we pull back and we say it'll be כשר
Kosher later today, it's a fit קרבן. Korban. Yes.
But there's a big difference here. If I say זו פסח Zo
Pesach on the morning of the fourteenth of ניסן, Nisan,
automatically with me doing nothing else it's going to be... That's a
good point. With the עומר, Omer, someone has to do something.
That's a good point too. I mean, you're right, it's a מצוה
Mitzvah to do it and we should assume it's going to be
done, but that's a good point too in addition to the fact
that there's an active פסול Psul here as opposed to just it's
not yet the time, the point is also that it's not just
that the time will come about naturally, it needs an act to
be done. So you're right, so both of those are חידושים Chidushim
here about applying this principle.
Okay, מיתיבי רב אדא בריה דרב יצחק, Maitivi Rav Adda brei d'Rav
Yitzchak, יש בעופות שאין במנחות יש במנחות שאין בעופות. Yesh b'ofot she'ein
b'menachot yesh b'menachot she'ein b'ofot. Here's a ברייתא Braita that says there
are things that apply to birds that don't apply to מנחות Menachot
and vice versa. יש בעופות שהעופות באים בנדבת שנים, Yesh b'ofot sheha'ofot
ba'im b'nidvat shnayim, birds can come with a שותפות Shutfut in partnership.
You can have two people that jointly bring a bird קרבן, Korban,
whereas you cannot have two people that jointly bring a מנחה Mincha
קרבן. Korban. By a מנחה Mincha it says נפש כי תקריב, Nefesh
ki takriv, it can only be brought by an individual. Partly the
reason is because a מנחה Mincha is a way of giving access
to even people that are on a low socioeconomic level, whatever, all
they can do is a little flour and oil. So you know
at that level you don't want to be going so much that
you're saying, oh, two people can partner it, like this is already
the minimum thing and therefore you know it's only an individual, so
it doesn't come in partnership. I remember that my cousin told me
that he was once in ישראל Yisrael and he went to this
שטיבל, Shtiebel, and the שטיבל, Shtiebel, this was going way way back,
you know, and it said like when, remember they had what was
the גרוש Grush they used to have as like a,
no no no, the small coins in ישראל Yisrael way back like,
what were they? Not a שקל. Shekel. It was like an אגורה
Agura I guess. Yeah, okay anyway, so something, anyway, so there was
a... so every time everybody got an עליה, Aliyah, they would always
say, they would always say, you know, מתנה, Matana, right? And then
who knows what they would give. So there was a little sign
that said like something
like אין מתנה פחותה מעשרים אגורות. Ein matana p'chuta m'esrim agurot. Okay,
so a guy gets an עליה Aliyah and after his עליה Aliyah
they give him a מי שבירך, Mi Sheberach, he says חצי מתנה.
Chatzi matana.
All right, so you can't do that, you can't give a חצי
מתנה, Chatzi matana, you can't give a half of a מנחה. Mincha.
All right, okay.
ומחוסרי כפרה, Umchusrei Kapara, so okay, שהעופות באים בנדבת שנים, sheha'ofot ba'im
b'nidvat shnayim, but birds come in
partnership, ומחוסרי כפרה, umchusrei kapara, birds are used for somebody or are
used almost always basically for in a purification process when somebody needs
a קרבן Korban to change their Halachic status, okay, they're always a,
you know, or at least an option, והותרו מכלל איסורן בקודש, v'hutru
miklal issuran bakodesh, and in this context in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash something that normally would be טריפה Treifa is מותר Muttar because
you do מליקה Melika on a bird, whereas that's not true by
a מנחה, Mincha, you don't have it becoming מותר Muttar when it
otherwise would be טריפה. Treifa. מה שאין כן במנחות, Ma she'ein ken
b'menachot, which isn't true by מנחות. Menachot. ויש במנחות, V'yesh b'menachot, what
do you have by מנחות Menachot that aren't true about birds? שהמנחות
טעונות כלי. Shehamenachot te'unot kli. First of all you put them in
a כלי שרת, Kli Shareit, whereas by birds you use the finger
of a כהן, Kohen, you don't do a כלי שרת. Kli Shareit.
ותנופה, Ut'nufa, there's a waving, והגשה, V'hagasha, you touch it to the
corner. know of the altar, וישנן בציבור כביחיד, ve-yeshnan be-tzibur ke-be-yachid, you
have a communal מנחה mincha like מנחת עומר, minchas omer, you don't
have any communal bird sacrifices, מה
שאין כן בעופות. mah she-ken be-ofos. Okay. ואי איתא Ve-im issa now
if this statement is correct that you actually can bring a מנחת
עומר minchas omer that was פסול, pasul, I mean that wasn't מתיר,
matir, okay, so while the grain was still אסור, assur, במנחות נמי
משכחת לה דהותרה מכלל איסור בקודש, be-menachos nami mishkachas lah de-hutra mikhlal
issur be-kodesh, then you have a case by a מנחה mincha where
also you can bring something on the מזבח mizbeach that was that
is basically not kosher to be eaten. Right? It said only birds
you can bring something that otherwise would not be kosher, מליקה. melikah.
But look, I can give you a מנחה mincha that's you that
you can bring that's not kosher to be eaten, this case where
you did the מנחת עומר שלא לשמו, minchas omer shelo lishmo, and
it's טרף treif grain and you're still bringing it on the מזבח.
mizbeach. But aren't you talking about things that happened בדיעבד? be-diavad?
All right, that's true. Okay, ומאי ני? u-mai ni? מנחת עומר. minchas
omer. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara is answering. כיון דאין
מחוסר זמן לבו ביום לאו איסורא הוא. keivan de-ein mechusar zman le-bo
be-yom lav issura hu. No, no, says the גמרא, Gemara, you missed
the point. Since the whole reason this מנחת עומר minchas omer is
kosher is because we say you pull back and you look at
the whole its status later today and later today it will be
kosher and that makes it kosher now, then it's not a good
example of something that's טרף treif that's offered on the מזבח mizbeach
because the whole reason it is offered on the מזבח mizbeach is
because we don't consider it טרף treif because we're looking at it
later today, at what its status will be later today. So it's
not a good example of something that's really טרף treif that's offered
on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay. מתיב רב ששת, masiv Rav Sheshes, so
רב ששת Rav Sheshes challenged this argument. הקדים מתן שמן למתן דם,
hikdim matan shemen le-matan dam, so let's say you have by the
מצורע, metzora, you went ahead and what you're supposed to do is
you're supposed to put the blood on his thumb and then you're
supposed to put the oil. And you did it out of order.
You did the oil first and then the blood. ימלאנו שמן ויחזור
ויתן שמן אחר. yimle'enu shemen ve-yachzor ve-yitein shemen acher. So now you
have you did oil, blood, so the blood was right, the oil
was wrong, so now fill up the לוג log with oil, get
a because you have to be operating out of a full לוג,
log, and now do oil a second time on top of the
blood because at least the blood was right. Okay.
ויחזור ויתן שמן אחר מתן דם. ve-yachzor ve-yitein shemen achar matan dam.
מתן בהונות למתן שבע, matan be-honos le-matan sheva, now let's say you
put it on the thing on the thumbs before you sprinkled the
oil, you know you're supposed to sprinkle the oil seven times. So
but you did the thumb thing before you sprinkled the oil.
Okay, so so but at least you sprinkled the oil correctly. You
did thumbs and then sprinkling. So the sprinkling was correct, but the
thumbs was too early. So what do you do? ימלאנו שמן ויחזור
ויתן מתן בהונות אחר מתן שבע. yimle'enu shemen ve-yachzor ve-yitein matan be-honos
achar matan sheva. So fill up the לוג log again and now
put the thumbs on, so now you'll get the thumbs after the
oil. Okay. But the problem all of these things was that you
went out of order. Okay. But the גמרא Gemara has a question.
But why is that considered out of order or a problem? ואי
אמרת אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום, ve-i amarta ein mechusar zman le-bo
be-yom, so this isn't exactly the same, this isn't something טרף treif
that we're going to say it's like it's kosher because it'll be
kosher later, but it's the same idea. If we pull back and
just say, if today is the day of something, it's considered its
time even now. So even so today would be the day, that's
the broad, you know, abstract way of looking at it. Today is
the day of bringing a מנחה mincha from the new grain because
we're going to bring the עומר omer later, so therefore it's kosher
even even if it was brought earlier today. Okay. By the way,
let me just pause for a moment and say, let's say Michael
here, not as a מנחת עומר, minchas omer, he just brings his
מנחה mincha on the second day of פסח Pesach and he brings
it from, you know, from grain that he harvested, you know, he
violated or maybe somebody cut it for him and cut the grain
before the עומר omer was brought. Okay. Made his מנחה mincha out
of it, has totally טרף, treif, you know, flour in his home
because the מנחה mincha hasn't been brought and he brings it the
morning of the sixteenth of פסח. Pesach. Okay. Forget it, the מנחת
עומר minchas omer is going to be brought totally kosher, but it's
going to be brought later today. Is that קרבן korban kosher? And
according to this, the answer is that קרבן korban is kosher. Why?
Because it'll be because later today is a proper time for it.
So even now is considered a proper time and again we don't
look at the fact that it's טרף, treif, we just say later
today will be a proper time, later today it won't be טרף.
treif. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's the principle of אין
מחוסר זמן לבו ביום, ein mechusar zman le-bo be-yom, so why does
it matter that you went out of order and you did the,
you know, you did sort of the oil before you did the
blood? But later later today it'll be the time for the oil,
so the time for the oil could also be earlier. And just
because you did it before the right time, and again it's sort
of like Charlie's point, it's not just before the right time, oh
the time is 2:00 PM. The time is defined by something else
being done, right? So by the עומר omer you brought it before
the עומר omer was brought, but it's okay, since it'll be kosher
after the עומר omer was brought and that's happening later today, it's
kosher before. So since the putting of the you blood on, you
know, the oil on the finger will be kosher after the blood
is put on, it's kosher even before. But the תורה Torah told
you to
do it in a specific order.
Right. So the difference is is that there the תורה Torah is
describing a sequence, right? Whereas by here the issue about bringing a
מנחה mincha too early even though the stuff might be טרף, treif,
the תורה Torah hasn't defined a sequence of of rituals, you know,
it's just... just like, oh, that was too early, oh, but it'll
be כשר kosher later, right? But here there's like a sequence and
the תורה Torah might say this sequence is the way the sequence
has to be done, which is essentially what the גמרא Gemara answers.
Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara answer is: Okay. אמר רב פפא ואימא
ואי אמרת אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום אמאי יחזור ויתן מאי דעבד
עבד,
Amar Rav Papa ve-eima ve-i amrat ein mechusar
zman le-vo beyom amai yachzor ve-yitein mai de-avad avad,
what you did was should be good. אמר רב פפא שאני הלכות
מצורע דכתיב בהו הוויה. Amar Rav Papa shani hilchos metzora de-chsiv behu
havayah. There's a פסוק pasuk that says shall be, it is, which
means that the sequence is fixed and it has to be done
with this sequence. דאמר קרא וזאת תהיה תורת המצורע תהיה, De-amar kra
ve-zos tihiyeh Torat HaMetzora tihiyeh, it should be exactly this way, בהווייתה
תהא, be-havayatah tehei, exactly in this state. Okay, so מתיב רב פפא,
Maysiv Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa asked: הקדים חטאתו לאשמו
לא יהא אחר ממרס בדמו אלא תעובר צורתה ותצא לבית שריפה. Hikdim
chatato le-ashamo lo yehei acher memares bedamo ela te'ubar tzuratah ve-teitzei le-veit
sereifa.
So what happens if you actually
שחט shachted the חטאת, chatat, I think this is by a מצורע,
metzora,
you שחט shachted the חטאת chatat before the אשם? asham? And it's
supposed to be first you bring the אשם asham and then you
bring the חטאת. chatat. But you שחט shachted the חטאת chatat before
the אשם. asham. So why don't you say: Okay, but we can
still get the אשם asham to be thrown, the blood, first? Stir
the blood of the חטאת, chatat, okay, have somebody to keep it
from congealing, שחט shacht the אשם, asham, bring the אשם asham and
then bring the חטאת. chatat. That should seem that that should work.
That'll get us back to our right order. It says: Don't do
that. Rather, what do you do? אלא תעובר צורתה, Ela te'ubar tzuratah,
wait for the meat to become פסול בלינה, pasul bi-linah, ותצא לבית
שריפה, ve-teitzei le-veit sereifa, and then go ahead and burn it. Okay,
so fine, we don't want you to stir. Now why we don't
want you to stir we're not going to worry about right now,
but the point is fundamentally that's the principle that if the חטאת
chatat was done before the
אשם, asham, it's too early and it's פסול. pasul. But why is
it too early? Why don't we just say: It'll be its time
later today?
ואמאי? Ve-amai? So the גמרא Gemara now says: Before you even
get to articulating the question,
the גמרא Gemara says: Wait a minute, this is part of the
rituals of מצורע. metzora. We already gave you an answer that there's
a sequence by the rituals of מצורע, metzora, it's not just some
other problem that is making it not yet its time. So the
גמרא Gemara says: אמאי קא מתיב רב פפא? Amai ka maysiv Rav
Papa? Why is רב פפא Rav Papa asking? והא רב פפא הוא
דאמר שאני הלכות מצורע דכתיב בהו הוויה. Ve-ha Rav Papa hu de-amar
shani hilchos metzora de-chsiv behu havayah. רב פפא Rav Papa just said
that within the rituals of מצורע metzora there's a sequence and the
sequence has to be fixed. Okay, אלא רב פפא הכי קא קשיא
ליה. Ela Rav Papa hachi ka kashya leih. No, no, this is
what was bothered him: אימא הני מילי עבודה שחיטה לאו עבודה היא.
Eima hanei mili avoda shechita lav avoda hi.
Maybe the idea of the fixed rituals are things that are considered
part of the עבודות, avodot, part of the actual, you know,
a temple עבודה. avoda. But שחיטה shechita is not generally considered an
עבודה. avoda. Now I'm going to get back to that in a
minute why that's true. Okay, but so therefore he felt that that
at least, שחיטה, shechita, it should not be the answer that the
תורה Torah fixed the order of the rituals of the עבודות, avodot,
because שחיטה shechita isn't an עבודה. avoda. And therefore the only point
here is not that it's like fixed in a sequence of rituals,
but that it's just considered too early. Well why is too early
a problem if you said אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום? Ein mechusar
zman le-vo beyom? So the גמרא Gemara says: ואי אמרת אין מחוסר
זמן לבו ביום יהא אחר ממרס בדמו ולאקרובי אשם והדר לאקרובי חטאת.
Ve-i amrat ein mechusar zman le-vo beyom yehei acher memares bedamo u-le-akruvei
asham ve-hadar le-akruvei chatat. Go ahead and bring the אשם asham and
then bring the חטאת. chatat. Now again, we're not even saying that
you should be allowed to bring the חטאת chatat first, okay? You
know, because again, bringing the חטאת chatat and throwing the blood, that
actually is an עבודה. avoda. All what we're saying is that the
שחיטה shechita out of order shouldn't be a problem because that's not
an עבודה. avoda. Now of course תוספות Tosafot asks: Wait a minute,
you can't do the שחיטה shechita without the קבלת הדם, kabbalas hadam,
the קבלת הדם kabbalas hadam is an עבודה. avoda. But okay, let's
bracket that. But the question is: Why is doing the שחיטה shechita
early a problem? Why don't we say אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום,
Ein mechusar zman le-vo beyom, and I don't think that you can
just say here: This is just the rituals of a מצורע metzora
and it has to be in a fixed order. So why is
it a problem that the שחיטה shechita was done a little early?
So אלא אמר רב פפא היינו טעמא דריש לקיש. Ela amar Rav
Papa hainu ta'ama de-Resh Lakish. You're right. Forget this idea of אין
מחוסר זמן לבו ביום. Ein mechusar zman le-vo beyom. Now it doesn't
mean we totally forget it. אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום Ein mechusar
zman le-vo beyom is still relevant when the only problem is time.
The problem isn't out of order. Like I said, the problem is
you sanctified your קרבן פסח korban Pesach in the morning of the
14th. We still say it for
that. But we're not going to say אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום
Ein mechusar zman le-vo beyom to say that if actually something is
טרף, treif, like the grain before the עומר Omer was brought, or
if something was done out of order, that אין מחוסר זמן ein
mechusar zman is relevant. אין מחוסר זמן Ein mechusar zman is relevant
when the only problem is early, is that it's not yet, you
know, the time on the clock hasn't come yet. As Charlie said,
that happens naturally. The problem is time. When the problem is order
or the problem is something else like it's טרף treif or whatever,
אין מחוסר זמן ein mechusar zman is not relevant. So if that's
true, why did רייש לקיש Resh Lakish say this is a כשר
kosher קרבן? korban? The grain is טרף. treif. Okay. So what's the
reason of רייש לקיש? Resh Lakish? אלא אמר רב פפא היינו טעמא
דריש לקיש, Ela amar Rav Papa hainu ta'ama de-Resh Lakish, this is
the reason of רייש לקיש, Resh Lakish, דקסבר האיר מזרח מתיר. de-kasvar
he'ir mizrach matir. He actually holds that the grain becomes כשר kosher
at the daybreak of the 16th, that you don't need the עומר
Omer to be brought. The עומר Omer is not really what's מתיר.
matir. what's really מתיר matir. *matir* is the day that the עומר
omer. *Omer* is brought, and the daybreak is מתיר matir, *matir*. Now
before we get on to develop that, I just want to say
something about שחיטה shchita, *shechita* is not an עבודה avoda. *avoda*, which
was a theme that we had, you know, throughout מסכת זבחים Zevachim
*Masechet Zevachim*, why is it not an עבודה avoda *avoda*? So תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* asks that question, you know, what does it mean to
say it's not an עבודה avoda. *avoda*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* first
says it's not an עבודה avoda? *avoda* because a non כהן kohen
*kohen* can do it. Okay, but then תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is bothered
by this, a non כהן kohen *kohen* can sometimes do other things
as well, you know, other types of פסולים *pesulim* are sometimes כשר
kasher *kosher*, like the left hand, but anyway, but the point is,
here you never require a כהן kohen *kohen* for שחיטה *shechita*. So
that's reason signal number one that it's not an עבודה avoda? *avoda*.
Signal number two that it's not an עבודה avoda *avoda*, as תוספות
*Tosafot* says, is the fact that even when you're eating meat outside
of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit Hamikdash* you need to do
שחיטה *shechita*. And there's no special הלכה *halacha* of שחיטה *shechita* that
applies by a קרבן korban *korban* that doesn't apply by anything else.
Okay, and
therefore conceptually, this is a very powerful point, it's not a temple
ritual, right? It's just that, you know, sort of like we just
said now, well you're not going to use טרף treif. *treif* meat
on the מזבח *mizbeach*, you need to get, you know, so therefore
you're obviously going to שחט shacht *shecht* it in the way that
makes it כשר kasher *kosher*, but the שחיטה *shechita* is completely defined
by שחיטה *shechita*, the laws of שחיטה *shechita* that apply by any
animal. And therefore it's a non עבודה *avoda* act that is necessary
to be done, you know, in order to eventually use the meat
as a קרבן korban *korban*. Okay, but ultimately it's fundamentally rooted in
the fact, not in the fact that it's a קרבן korban. *korban*,
but just it's what you need to do to get the meat
to the next stage because that's what you need to do to
get any meat to the next stage. Okay, that's a second explanation.
The third explanation points to the fact that the שוחט shocheting? *shochet*
doesn't have to be standing in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit
Hamikdash*, and if it were an עבודה *avoda* you would have to
be standing in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*. Here you
could be standing outside with a long knife and so on. Anyway,
very interesting תוספות *Tosafot*, שחיטה לאו עבודה *shechita lav avoda*, he that
he works through different ways of conceptualizing that. Wait, let's just turn
the page. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, דרבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש אמרי תרוייהו *de-Rabbi Yochanan ve-Reish Lakish amri tavaihu*, so here's why
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* says it's not a טרף treif?
*treif* קרבן korban? *korban*, because רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* and
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* both say אפילו בזמן שבית המקדש
קיים *afilu b'zman she-Beit Hamikdash kayyam*, like it's not just that when
there's no בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* and there's no עומר omer *Omer*
then there's a debate, what's מתיר matir? *matir*, the morning of the
sixteenth, the morning of the seventeenth, that's a debate, but that's when
there's no עומר Omer *Omer*. But even when there is an עומר
Omer. *Omer* and you would think that if there is an עומר
Omer *Omer* it's going to be the עומר Omer *Omer* that is
going to be מתיר matir *matir*, no. Even when the בית המקדש
*Beit Hamikdash* is around, האיר מזרח מתיר matir? *he'ir mizrach matir*. Okay,
it is the daybreak that permits it of the sixteenth. והדר ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish, בפירוש דאיתמר לכללה איתמר *ve-hadar Reish Lakish be-feirush d'itmar
le-michlala itmar*. He didn't say that explicitly, it was implicit, דתנן *de-tenan*.
אין מביאין מנחת ביכורים ומנחת בהמה קודם לעומר *Ein mevi'in minchat bikkurim
u-minchat behema kodem la-Omer*. You don't bring, now our גרסה *girsa* is
מנחת ביכורים *minchat bikkurim* which doesn't really make sense. So the side
גרסה *girsa* say אין מביאין מנחות Menachos. וביכורים ומנחת בהמה *ein mevi'in
menachot u-vikkurim u-minchat behema*, so מנחת בהמה *minchat behema* would be the
מנחת נסכים *minchat nesachim* that comes with an animal. Okay, you don't
bring any of that קודם לעומר *kodem la-Omer*, before the עומר Omer
*Omer*, ואם הביא פסול pasul *ve-im heivi pasul*. And if you brought
it, it's פסול pasul *pasul* because again it's not כשר kasher *kosher*
food being brought as a קרבן korban. *korban*. קודם לשתי הלחם *kodem
li-shtei halechem*, don't bring it before the two loaves that are brought
on שבועות *Shavuot*, לא יביא *lo yavi* you're not bringing, ואם הביא
כשר kasher *ve-im heivi kasher* and if you brought it it's כשר
kasher *kosher*. Why? Because it's כשר kosher. *kosher* food. The reason that
you don't bring it before the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* on שבועות
*Shavuot* is because the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* on שבועות *Shavuot*, which
is out of wheat as opposed to the עומר omer *Omer* which
is out of barley, the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* on שבועות *Shavuot*
are supposed to be the קרבן korban. ראשית *korban reshit*, are supposed
to be like the first קרבן korban *korban* in the בית המקדש
*Beit Hamikdash* from the new grain other than the עומר *Omer*. So
the הלכה *halacha* is that קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot* are supposed to, new
קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* from the new produce are only supposed to come
after the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*. Okay, but that's the idea, the
שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* is supposed to be the ביכורים *bikkurim*, the
first, okay, of the new stuff brought in the בית המקדש *Beit
Hamikdash*. But if you violated that, you did not, the קרבן korban.
*korban* is not invalid because at the end of the day, the
קרבן korban, *korban* is still made out of food that could be
eaten by a normal person. From the time the עומר *Omer* was
brought, the קרבן korban, *korban* was made out of food, it was
כשר kosher *kosher* food. So even though it violated the principle that
ביכורים *bikkurim* are supposed to be the first, you know, sometimes you
can violate some of those rules and it doesn't invalidate the קרבן
korban *korban*. So therefore if you brought it before שבועות *Shavuot* it's
כשר kosher *kosher*, if you brought it before פסח *Pesach* it's not
כשר kosher *kosher* because it's not כשר kosher *kosher* food. Now by
the way I'll just mention parenthetically, it's very interesting if your גרסה
*girsa* is ביכורים *bikkurim* here, מנחות וביכורים *menachot u-vikkurim*, that ביכורים *bikkurim*
are on the list for bringing it before the עומר *Omer* it's
invalid. Why when you bring ביכורים *bikkurim* before the עומר *Omer* is
it invalid? ביכורים *bikkurim* are fruit, they're not your grain, they're not
טרף treif, *treif* to be eaten before the עומר *Omer*. So maybe
it's being only in that list because of the שתי הלחם *shtei
halechem* part, not because of the עומר *Omer* part. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute, ואמר רבי יצחק אמר ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish *ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak amar Reish Lakish*, לא שנו אלא ארבעה עשר
*lo shanu ela arba'a asar*. When is it if you brought these
קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* before the עומר *Omer* that they're invalid? That's only
if you brought them on the ארבעה עשר *arba'a asar*, the fourteenth
of ניסן *Nisan*, ובחמישה עשר *u-vachamisha asar*, or the חמישה עשר *hamisha
asar*, the fifteenth. אבל בשישה עשר *aval be-shisha asar*, if you brought
them on the שישה עשר *shisha asar*, the sixteenth of ניסן *Nisan*,
אם הביא כשר kosher, *im heivi kasher*, they're כשר kosher *kosher* even
though they're before the עומר *Omer*. So I don't know what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means that that's implicit, I mean, okay, it's not
explicit. that's explicit, but it's pretty clear. Why is it כשר kosher,
if you bring it the morning of the sixteenth? It must be
אלמא קסבר האיר המזרח מתיר alma kasavar he-ir hamizrach matir that the
new grain is permissible as soon as daybreak. I guess the reason
that it's not seen as explicit is because we just got through
a whole earlier discussion that maybe you could say no, the grain
is still טרף. treif, Why would it be כשר kosher if you
brought it the morning of the sixteenth even if it's still טרף?
treif! Because you could say אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום. ein mechussar
zman l'vo b'yom. You know, the idea we were saying at the
beginning of the דף. daf. Maybe the grain is טרף, treif! but
we look at the status of the קרבן korban based on what
it'll be later today. So that's why his statement is not explicit.
Okay, it's really a reiteration of the earlier point, that if you
bring a קרבן korban of grain on the morning of the sixteenth,
it's still כשר kosher? even before the עומר. But there are two
ways of explaining it. Number one, אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום ein
mechussar zman l'vo b'yom which we reject, and number two, what we're
saying is actually the same thing that apparently רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
said explicitly, that actually no, it's not טרף, treif! that actually even
for everybody, not just in terms of the status of קרבנות, korbanot,
for everybody, the new grain is permissible already the morning of the
sixteenth. Yes, Charlie, you had a point?
I just want to say I saw the same statement by רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
There you go. Good to know that there are parallel traditions.
Okay, this is
maybe what רבא Rava is going to say coming up. I don't
know. But according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish then why would you
need to even bring a second—Right,
so the גמרא Gemara is going to say why do you bring
the עומר at all together? Or why do you need to bring
a second one before you eat the first one? Before you eat
the first one. Right, so that's excellent. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to say that. Okay, ורבא אמר, v'Rava amar, now רבא Rava
said, מנחת העומר שקמצה שלא לשמה כשרה ושייריה נאכלין. minchas ha'omer she'kamtza
she'lo lishma kesheira v'shireha ne'echalin.
So he actually says that he does ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, one
step further. It's כשר kosher even though it wasn't מתיר. matir? Okay,
okay, it wasn't מתיר, matir? it's still כשר kosher and you bring
it, but you can eat the remainder. Now, why can you eat
the remainder? Okay, ואינה צריכה מנחת עומר אחרת v'eina tzericha minchas omer
acheres and you don't need another מנחת עומר minchas omer להתירה. l'hatira.
Why? Wait, so wait, so even though it was שלא לשמה, she'lo
lishma, it's effective? Why is it effective שלא לשמה? she'lo lishma? He
says you don't even need to bring another מנחת עומר. minchas omer.
If it was שלא לשמה she'lo lishma and it's not עלה לבעלים
לשם חובה, ala l'ba'alim l'shem chova, shouldn't that mean that it's not
effective and it's not מתיר? matir So he says no, שאין
מחשבה מועלת אלא במי שראוי לעבודה. she'ein machshava mo'eles ela b'mi she'ra'uy
l'avoda. A bad thought, like שלא לשמה, she'lo lishma, is only meaningful
if it is in something that has traction. Somebody like if somebody
who's a non-כהן Kohen, has a פיגול piggul thought, that's not meaningful.
Okay.
Even when שוחט-ing?
Well, that would be considered I guess ראוי ra'uy for that עבודה.
Okay, but let's say for the other עבודות. avodos. ובדבר הראוי לעבודה,
u'v'davar ha'ra'uy l'avoda, it has to be with a thing that is
fit for a קרבן. korban ובמקום הראוי לעבודה u'v'makom ha'ra'uy l'avoda in
a right place. Now we're going to explain this. במי שראוי לעבודה
לאפוקי כהן בעל מום. b'mi she'ra'uy l'avoda l'afokei kohen ba'al mum. Again,
not by the שחיטה, by the other acts. If it was a
non-כהן Kohen or כהן בעל מום, kohen ba'al mum, if he had
a פיגול piggul thought it would not. Now, the fact that a
non-כהן Kohen. did the עבודה might invalidate, but maybe not. Like you
might remember, let's say it was הולכה, holacha, there's a whole question
about can you just move it back and do the הולכה holacha
again. So anyway, but certainly his thought doesn't invalidate if he's not
the right person that's supposed to be doing it. ובדבר הראוי לעבודה
u'v'davar ha'ra'uy l'avoda and it also doesn't invalidate a wrong thought if
it's not a thing that's fit for the עבודה. What's a thing
that's not fit for the
עבודה? מנחת העומר. minchas ha'omer. The מנחת העומר. minchas ha'omer. Wait, why
is it not fit for עבודה? דלא חזיא דחידוש הוא. d'lo chazya
d'chidush hu. That's not fit because the whole thing is a חידוש.
chidush. I'll get back to that in a minute, let's just finish
the sentence. ובמקום הראוי לעבודה לאפוקי נפגם המזבח. u'v'makom ha'ra'uy l'avoda l'afokei
nifgam ha'mizbeach. It has to be the right place, if for some
reason, you know, the right context, if for some reason the altar
had a chip and therefore קרבנות Korbanot were פסול pasul for this
minute while we were fixing the chip and you at that minute
had a bad thought, your bad thought did not invalidate and now
the chip is fixed and now you can keep on doing it.
So your bad thoughts only invalidate it when, you know, you have
what I'll say has traction, when you're sort of in the right
place and context and so on and therefore, you know, it's a
meaningful act and therefore your thought invalidates. Now, why are we saying
your thought does not invalidate by a מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer because
a מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer is not a fit קרבן? korban So
we actually רש"י Rashi says something, I don't want to sort of
say what רש"י Rashi says because תוספות says the more obvious thing.
Why do you think it's saying that a מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer
is not something fit to be offered and therefore thought does not
invalidate? What does it mean that the מנחת העומר minchas omer is
not fit to be offered?
Or maybe I just—Go ahead. You look—No idea.
Use barley, it's not—That's what רש"י Rashi says. That's not the פשט.
pshat. No, come on. What did we just say? What's the problem
with a מנחת העומר? minchas ha'omer? It's טרף! treif It's טרף! traif.
Until it's brought, it itself is טרף! traif Even when it's going
to be done correctly. Okay? So if you think about it, I
take this קומץ kometz and I'm putting this קומץ kometz on the
fire. The moment I'm putting it on, I have טרף traif grain
in my hand, okay, which is something that should not be brought
as a קרבן. korban At the moment that it's brought,
it sort of, you know, that at that very second it becomes
a כשר קרבן. korban, קרבן korban. it makes itself כשר. Okay, but
in the process of doing it it was still טרף. traif It's
only going to be כשר grain after it's brought. So here I
am I'm taking the קמיצה kemitza and I'm thinking שלא לשמה. shelo
lishma. Well I'm taking—I'm doing it while I'm doing an עבודה on
something that by all rights should not be a כשר קרבן. korban
Okay? So that's what the גמרא Gemara says, it's a חידוש. chiddush.
Yes, it shouldn't be a כשר קרבן, korban. but in the context
of מתיר matir the grain, it itself is acceptable. But based on
normal principles, this is—this is טרף traif. food. So therefore my thought
doesn't invalidate. So what רבא Rava says is that because of the
bizarre nature of the קרבן העומר, korban ha'omer, that it itself by
rights should not be a כשר קרבן, korban therefore it's excluded from
the הלכות halachos that your thoughts invalidate. And therefore your thoughts don't
invalidate and it's totally operate. So that's רבא's Rava's עסק. esek. Now
we didn't get back to David's question because that wasn't what רבא
Rava was saying. I'm sorry, it was actually רש"י Rashi says. David
says, "So I don't get it, according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish.
okay, if the grain is permissible, I understand why you're going to
bring an עומר later that day because there's a מצוה mitzvah to
bring an עומר. And this one you invalidate—whatever, you did it שלא
לשמה." shelo lishma. But why does ריש לקיש Resh Lakish. say not
eat the grain if actually the grain is permissible from the beginning
of the day? So that's a good question. So רש"י Rashi I
believe answers that. Let's check. רש"י Rashi, says,
okay,
he says like this:
four lines down from the top of רש"י, Rashi the bottom of
the wide lines at the top. So רש"י answers the question. So
he says, והא דאין שיריה נאכלים, veha de'ein shireiha ne'echalim, so why
does ריש לקיש Resh Lakish say don't eat the שיריים shirayim if
he says that the beginning of the day is
מתיר? matir דמצוה להמתין עד הבאת העומר demitzvah lehamtin ad hava'at ha'omer
כדאמר ריש לקיש פרק ר' ישמעאל kide'amar Resh Lakish Perek Rabi Yishmael
והכתיב עד הביאכם vehaktiv ad havi'achem ומשני למצוה. umeshani lemitzvah. So the
same reason we ask by ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish one minute, what
do you mean that the beginning of the daybreak is מתיר? matir
The פסוק passuk says, ולחם וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו עד הביאכם velechem
vekali vekarmel lo tochlu ad havi'achem את קרבן אלהיכם. at korban elokeichem.
It says don't eat the grain until the קרבן korban, is brought.
What do you mean the beginning of the day is מתיר? matir
So he says, no, the איסור issur goes away, the negative
prohibition goes away by daybreak. But it says you
shouldn't—is that a מצות עשה, mitzvah aseh, is that an ideal? But
whatever, there's a מצוה mitzvah to wait till the עומר is brought,
but it's really not טרף traif. already from the beginning of daybreak.
But there's a מצוה mitzvah to wait.
So he contradicts תוספות then, that you were saying before it's טרף
traif until it—and he's saying it's not טרף. traif No, ריש לקיש.
Resh Lakish. No, ריש לקיש. Yeah, no, before the גמרא Gemara said
it is—it is טרף. traif. Well, oh, you mean this second point
of רבא. Rava. Yeah, yeah, let's ignore רבא. Rava. Let's—yes, let's not
mix it up. Hold on, let me first—I'll repeat the רבא Rava
point, okay. ריש לקיש and רבי יוחנן say it's מותר mutar at
the beginning of the day. That's why the קרבן Korban. is כשר,
why even if you did it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. Why do
you not eat the remnant? The same reason everybody in their home
shouldn't eat the—shouldn't eat their new grain until the עומר is brought.
Although the prohibition goes away at the beginning of the day, the
מצוה mitzvah is you wait till after the קרבן is brought. So
here for this case, that's true in your home as well. Don't
start eating it beginning of the day, start eating it after—if you
ate it at the beginning of the day, you didn't transgress, but
wait till the קרבן is brought. So here too when you did
it שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, okay, it's כשר because the grain is
כשר, but don't eat the remnant until the עומר will be brought.
That's ריש לקיש who says it's מותר mutar at the beginning of
the day. רב Rav says, or רבא Rava says, it's actually—it is
טרף traif, at the beginning of the day. He's not saying ריש
לקיש. It's טרף treif until the קרבן is brought. But he says
your שלא לשמה shelo lishma doesn't invalidate exactly because the קרבן is
טרף. treif, And because it's טרף, treif your שלא לשמה shelo lishma
doesn't invalidate. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
כשהוא אומר מן הבקר למטה, keshehu omer min habakar lemata, so now
we're going back to some זבחים thing, but we're going to circle
back to מנחות. When it says—תורה Torah says,
you know, אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן
הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם. adam ki yakriv mikem korban min habehema min
habakar u'min hatzon takrivu et korbanechem. Okay, so first it's—so from those
various things, מן הבהמה, min habehema, we learned to exclude animals of
bestiality, you know, מן הצאן, min hatzon, מן הבקר, min habakar, whatever,
we learned to use animals that weren't used in עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, all these types of exclusions. And then it says again, ואם
מן הבקר קרבנו. ve'im min habakar korbano. Okay, so it says מן
הבקר min habakar again. What is that coming to exclude? כשהוא אומר
מן הבקר למטה שאין תלמוד לומר אלא להוציא את הטרפה. keshehu omer
min habakar lemata she'ein talmud lomar ela l'hotzi et hatreifa. That's coming
to exclude an animal that's a טרפה. treifa. Okay, now, why do
we need a פסוק passuk to exclude an animal that's a טרפה?
treifa? This connects to our earlier theme. An animal that's a טרפה
treifa is already not כשר food. So why do you need a
פסוק passuk to exclude it?
Now, והלא דין הוא? vehalo din hu? One minute, we could have
excluded it based on logic. Why do you need a פסוק? passuk?
ומה בעל מום שמותר להדיוט אסור לגבוה, uma ba'al mum shemutar lehedyot
assur legavoah, a blemished animal that is permissible for a normal person
is forbidden for a
קרבן, טרפה שאסורה להדיוט אינו דין שאסורה לגבוה, treifa she'asura lehedyot eino
din she'asura legavoah, a טרפה treifa that can't be eaten by a
normal person, of course it should be אסור assur for a קרבן.
So he says no, חלב ודם יוכיחו. chelev vedam yochichu. That's not
necessarily true. The fat and the blood is a
counter-evidence שאסורין להדיוט sheasurin lhedyot that can't be eaten by a normal
person ומותרין לגבוה. umutarin legavoah. And they're permissible to a korban. So
therefore I would not have logically assumed that a טריפה treifa is
פסול as a korban. But the Gemara says wait, wait, wait, you
can't, no, no, חלב ודם chelev vedam is not relevant. מה לחלב
ודם שכן באים בכלל היתר. ma l'chelev vedam shekein ba'im b'klal heter.
חלב ודם chelev vedam comes from a kosher animal. Okay, the whole
animal as a whole is kosher. So it's one thing to say
these are the treif parts of an animal, fine, but the animal
as a whole is kosher. תאמר בטריפה שכולה אסורה. tomar b'treifa shekula
asura. By a טריפה treifa the whole animal is treif. So the
logic would dictate that if the whole animal is treif and a
normal person can't eat it, it can't be a korban. But the
Gemara says one minute, ולא תהא מותרת לגבוה. v'lo tei muteret legavoah.
Therefore it shouldn't be. So you don't need a פסוק, pasuk, logically
you should say it's treif. But the Gemara says no, מליקה תוכייח.
melika tochiyach. Wait, I wouldn't have necessarily known that. There's things that
the whole thing is treif that are good as a korban. A
bird that you did מליקה melika to, שכולו איסור ואסור להדיוט. shekulo
issur v'assur l'hedyot. That bird is all forbidden, it would be forbidden
to a normal person, ומותר לגבוה, umutar legavoah, and it's permissible to
a korban. So therefore I might think that טריפה treifa should be
permissible the same way מליקה melika is permissible. But the Gemara says
no, no, no, מה למליקה שכן קדושתה אסרתה. ma l'melika shekein kdushatah
asartah. By מליקה, melika, what makes it treif is a special ritual
you did for it because it's a korban and therefore, right, that's
what the korban ritual required. So the fact that we're going to
bracket its normal treif status because we demanded that that's how you
do the korban ritual, that's one thing. But something that's a טריפה
treifa from, you know, not related to the korban ritual and is
forbidden to a normal person, of course it should be forbidden. מה
שאין כן בטריפה שאין קדושתה אסרתה. ma she'ein kein b'treifa she'ein kdushatah
asartah. Okay, so therefore what it's basically saying is logically it seems
I could have concluded that a טריפה treifa is פסול for a
korban and I didn't need a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, and nevertheless, although
it seems I could have done it logically, ואם השיבוך, v'im hashevosa,
ואם השיבוך, v'im hashevosa, but if you came up with some retort,
you did come up with some argument to say that logically you
could have found a way to have argued that a טריפה treifa
would be good as a korban, so in order to respond to
whatever some mysterious argument you might have had, כשהוא אומר מן הבקר
למטה שאין תלמוד לומר להוציא את הטריפה, kshehu omer min habakar lemattah
she'ein talmud lomar l'hotzi et hatreifa, so the מן הבקר min habakar
is coming to exclude a טריפה. treifa. So it's a very bizarre
ברייתא braita you have this sometimes in מדרש הלכה. midrash halacha. Where
מדרש הלכה midrash halacha says the פסוק pasuk is coming to teach
you this. And then it says, wait, wait, I could have figured
that all out just by logic. And then it says, you know
what, it's true, you could have figured it out by logic, but
just in case you couldn't have, here's what the פסוק pasuk is
teaching you. So it's like, wait, but you just said that I
could have figured it out logically. So the Gemara comes to fill
the gap. The Gemara comes to say what in theory could you
have argued to have said that טריפה treifa was kosher that you
needed a פסוק pasuk for at the end of the day. It
sounds like you couldn't have made a cogent argument for טריפה treifa
to be a good korban. So that's what the Gemara asks. מאי
אם השיבוך, mai im hashavto, מאי אם השיבוך? mai im hashavto?
What is the thing you could have responded to? אמר רב משום
דאיכא למימר, amar rav mishum d'ika l'meimar, here's what you could have
argued by a טריפה. treifa. מנחת העומר תוכייח. minchat ha'omer tochiyach.
Now that's, now we see why we're bringing it in. Because there
are something that is treif that's a kosher korban. A מנחת העומר.
minchat ha'omer. Okay, מנחת העומר תוכייח שאסור להדיוט ומותר לגבוה. minchat ha'omer
tochiyach she'assur l'hedyot u'mutar legavoah.
So that's why I could have thought a טריפה treifa would be
okay. One minute, מה למנחת העומר שכן מתרת חדש. ma l'minchat ha'omer
shekein hateret chadash. No,
no, מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer is מתיר matir חדש. chadash. Now what
that means, I believe Rashi just says oh if it's powerful to
מתיר matir we're therefore going to say that we'll allow it even
though it's treif, but I don't think that's the point. I think
it's like the point that Tosfos said before. I think it's that
yes, but this is מתיר matir itself. So if it's coming along
and in the process it's מתיר matir itself, that's okay that in
that initially it's not kosher. Okay, something that's טריפה treifa and that's,
you know, and that even after you're done is going to remain
treif is obviously a different story than this which is מתיר matir
itself in the process. Is that what you were going to ask
Charlie?
I was just going to say,
זריקת הדם zrikat hadam is a מתיר matir for שלמים, shlamim, but
you but I think you addressed.
Yeah, yeah, but I think you're, yeah, no, it's מתיר matir the
איסור issur status here. So the Gemara says wait a minute, בשביעית,
bishvi'it, but I can still bring an example by
מנחת העומר minchat ha'omer on שמיטה. shmita. Where it's not a, apparently
it thinks that there's no grain to be מתיר matir on שמיטה.
shmita. Nobody is harvesting the grain or whatever, we'll get to that
in a minute, that's a pretty strange idea. So therefore it's not
functioning as a מתיר matir on שמיטה. shmita. Of course the point
I just said that it's מתיר mattir, itself, the Gemara is going
to get back to. Okay, but it's not מתיר mattir anything else
on שמיטה shmita and therefore you see an example of something that's
treif that's brought as a korban that's not מתיר matir anything. So
the Gemara says שביעית נמי שכן מתרת ספיחין בשביעית. shvi'it nami shekein
hateret sfichin bishvi'it. No, no, what do you mean? How about stuff
that grows wild? It still is מתיר matir stuff on שמיטה shmita
even though you're not planting and harvesting. I can't take this out.
Okay, it's still מתיר matir stuff that grows wild. So the Gemara
says כרבי עקיבא דאמר ספיחין אסורין בשביעית. k'rabbi akiva d'amar sfichin asurin
bishvi'it. No, Rabbi Akiva who says you're not allowed to even benefit
from the wild stuff, which normally we assume that to be rabbinic,
but it seems like the Gemara here is at least assuming that
it's de'oraita or whatever. Okay, so anyway, so therefore if there's no
permission to eat the wild grain, which is bizarre, what the heck
does that mean, right? It says like, you know, it should be
לבהמה, l'beheima, the Torah says it should be for the עניים aniyim
or whatever, so that gets into exactly the parameters of. what the
ספיחים sefichim refer to and what's its scope, anyway, way too complex
for what we're dealing with right now, but the גמרא Gemara basically
wants, imagines that during שמיטה Shemittah there's nothing left for it to
be מתיר, matir everything is אסור assur anyway, and therefore it's an
example of something that's טריף treif that's brought that's not מתיר matir
and you should say the same thing about טריפה. treifa. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אביי
לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Acha brei de-Rav Avya le-Rav Ashi, דרבי
עקיבא נמי לפרוך. d'Rabbi Akiva nami lifroch. Okay, but so what? Even
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, מה למנחת עומר שכן מתיר חדש
בחוצה לארץ. mah limnachat omer sheken matir chadash be-chutz la-aretz. Oh wait,
we didn't get to מתיר עצמה. matir atzmah. I'm jumping ahead. We're
going to get to there that it's מתיר matir itself. But he
says look, it's at least מתיר mattir חדש chadash outside ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, which is a big question, right? The איסור issur of
חדש chadash outside ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ואפילו מאן דאמר חדש בחוצה
לארץ לאו דאורייתא, v-afilu man de-amar chadash be-chutza la-aretz lav d'Oraita, even
if you think that it's not דאורייתא, d'Oraita, the implication of this
גמרא Gemara is that by default we should assume it is, and
that's overwhelmingly the position of the ראשונים Rishonim that חדש chadash outside
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is דאורייתא, d'Oraita, although there are a
few of the ראשונים Rishonim who think it isn't. But anyway, even
if you say it's not דאורייתא d'Oraita outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, שכן בא להתיר אף שבתוכה. she-ken ba le-hattir af she-be-tokhah. That's
finally the punchline. At the end of the day, the מנחת העומר
Minchat HaOmer is מתיר matir itself, even on שמיטה. Shemittah. Okay, the
grain of the מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer was אסור, assur, and after
you bring it, it's going to be מותר. muttar. It's מתיר matir
itself. So therefore of course מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer is okay even
though it's טריף, treif, because its whole thing is that it's טריף
treif and it's brought and then it's מתיר matir itself in the
process of being brought. But again, what is the argument to think
that an animal that is a טריפה treifa should be כשר? You
never have an animal that's a קרבן that's טריף. treif. So why
do I need a פסוק? pasuk? It should be obvious that it's
not good. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar lei
Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina, אי
הכי, i hachi, if that's true,
טריפה נמי תקריב ותתיר עצמה ותתיר אף שבתוכה. treifa nami takriv v-tattir
atzmah v-tattir af she-be-tokhah. That's a little bit crazy. He says, oh,
well then why don't we learn from that that that's the principle?
That you can bring something טריף treif and it can מתיר itself.
So you bring the עומר and it makes itself permissible, bring a
טריפה treifa and say in the context of bringing a טריפה, treifa,
it's now not כשר for let's say somebody else to eat, but
at least it's כשר as a קרבן. Maybe the process of bringing
it removes the problem. Of course that's bizarre because the תורה Torah
tells you that what the מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer does is it
has this מתיר effect. It's not intrinsic, anything brought as a קרבן
is מתיר itself. So the גמרא Gemara
says: אלא פרך הכי, Ela parch hachi, here's the point. מה מנחת
העומר שכן מצותה בכך, Mah Minchat HaOmer she-ken mitzvatah bekach, which is
that's the point. That is what the תורה Torah says. You bring
a מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer from the new grain, even though the
new grain is now אסור, assur, you bring it and then it's
מותר. muttar. A טריפה, treifa, there's nobody telling you to bring a
טריפה. treifa. So something that is fundamentally טריף treif that you're not
being told to brought, it's not like מליקה melikah that you're told
to do מליקה, melikah, it's not like מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer that
you're told to bring it from the grain even though the grain
is now אסור, assur, there's no logic to think that a טריפה
treifa would be okay. Okay, so why do you need a פסוק?
pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says: ריש לקיש אמר משום דאיכא למימר,
Reish Lakish amar mishum de-ika le-meimar, here's what you could have argued.
מפטם קטורת יוכיח שאסור להדיוט ומותר לגבוה. Mefatem ketoret yokhi'ach she-assur le-hediot
u-muttar le-gavoha. The guy who makes the קטורת, ketoret, you're not allowed
to pound the קטורת, ketoret, and nevertheless even though that's אסור assur
for a person to do for private, it's מותר muttar to do
for God. So the גמרא Gemara says: מפטם גברא הוא. mefatem gavra
hu. What do you mean מפטם? mefatem? That's the person who's doing
it. It's like somebody being nitpicking on your grammar. So the גמרא
Gemara says: No, פיטום הקטורת יוכיח. pitum haketoret yokhi'ach. Fine, fine, I
mean actually the not the person but the actual קטורת ketoret itself,
right, so that אסור להדיוט ומותר לגבוה. assur le-hediot u-muttar le-gavoha. That
again, that would be אסור, assur, you know, to be done to
sort of make the קטורת ketoret and whatever, that's אסור assur to
be done for private purposes and it's מותר muttar to be done,
you know, for the בית המקדש. So you see something that could
be considered טריף, treif, you know, is מותר muttar for the בית
המקדש. So again, the answer is obvious. No, מה פיטום הקטורת שכן
מצותה בכך. mah pitum haketoret she-ken mitzvatah bekach. But that's what the
תורה Torah is telling you to do! Okay, still doesn't prove the
טריפה treifa case. מר בריה דרבינא אמר משום דאיכא למימר שבת יוכיח.
Mar brei de-Ravina amar mishum de-ika le-meimar Shabbos yokhi'ach. How about שבת?
Shabbos? We have things that are מותר muttar for God that are
אסור assur for an individual. שאסור להדיוט, She-assur le-hediot, it's אסור assur
to שחט things on שבת, Shabbos, ומותר לגבוה, u-muttar le-gavoha, like certain
קרבנות Korbanot, on שבת, Shabbos, the at least the regular קרבנות, whatever.
No, מה שבת שכן הותר מכללו אצל הדיוט במילה. mah Shabbos she-ken
hutar mikhlalo etzel hediot be-milah.
So before it gets to מצותה בכך, mitzvatah bekach, which is the
obvious answer, it says: No, sometimes even a person is allowed to
do violate שבת, Shabbos, like for ברית מילה. brit milah. So the
גמרא says: מילה, milah, אטו מילה צורך הדיוט הוא? atu milah tzorach
hediot hu? No, no, no, wait a minute. That's not your personal
purpose. That's מילה מצוה הוא. milah mitzvah hu. You're still doing it
for God. So there are things that you're not allowed to violate
שבת Shabbos for your own interests. You're allowed to violate שבת Shabbos
though for God's interests, for bringing a קרבן, for מילה, milah, one
could also say פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, you know, ultimately that's because
the תורה Torah is telling you that that's of a higher purpose,
saving a life and so on. So you see something is אסור
assur for a person, for a private individual, and מותר muttar to
be done for God. So let's say the same type of thing
about a טריפה. treifa. So the גמרא says: No, אלא מה שבת
שכן מצותה בכך, ela mah Shabbos she-ken mitzvatah bekach, again it's... It's
not relevant. The תורה Torah tells you to bring certain קרבנות on
שבת. Shabbat. But by טרפה treifa it's not telling you if something
is just טרף treif and you're not told to do it this
way, there's no logic you should be able to do it as
a קרבן. So רב אדא בר אבא Rav Adda bar Abba אמר
משום דאיכא למימר כלאים תוכיח. amar mishum de'ika l'meimar Kilayim tochiach. How
about, now we're again moving outside of exactly קרבנות, how about שעטנז?
Shatnez? שאסור להדיוט, she'assur l'hedyot, a normal person isn't allowed to wear
שעטנז, Shatnez, ומותרין לגבוה, u'mutarin l'gavoha, but a כהן, the belt of
a כהן is שעטנז. Shatnez. So you see we permissed certain things
that are generally טרף, you know, not all, in the context of
the בית המקדש. מה לכלאים שכן הותרה מכללה אצל הדיוט בציצית. mah
l'kilayim shekein hutra miklala etzel hedyot betzitzit. No, because if you have
a linen garment you're allowed to have a wool ציצית, tzitzit, the
blue is wool, so you see it is permissible even for a
private individual. אטו ציצית צורך הדיוט הוא מצוה היא. atu tzitzit tzorech
hedyot hu mitzvah hi. No, no. We're not permitting it for you
for your personal use, we're permitting it for a מצוה. mitzvah. So
again, you have something that is טרף for you for a mundane
personal use and permissible in a religious context. So let's say the
same about an animal that's a טרפה. treifa. So again the גמרא
says that's not relevant, אלא מה לכלאים שמצוותה בכך. ela mah l'kilayim
shemitzvata bekach. That's the מצוה mitzvah of how you make the belt
of a כהן. Okay, so again, is there cases where the תורה
Torah will מתיר something in a מקדש Mikdash context that it forbids
elsewhere? Yes, when it explicitly is מתיר it, and when it says
this is how I want you to do it. But if something
is just סתם טרף, stam treif, we can't ignore it and say,
oh well, I'm using it for God, it's okay. All right, so
we still don't know, and again we have the general principle of
ממשקה ישראל. mimashke Yisrael. So we still don't know why you needed
a פסוק pasuk to exclude a טרפה treifa if logic should dictate
that something that generally is טרף and that the תורה Torah doesn't
explicitly allow, right, logic should dictate that therefore it's, sorry, logic should
dictate that therefore it should not be good and we should not
need a פסוק pasuk to tell us this. Okay, we will end.